布里 - 夏尔边境
跃马旅店
-小心点  -抱歉  亲爱的
- Watch it! - Sorry, darling.
-给  -谢谢
- Here you are. - Thank you.
我可以坐这吗
Mind if I join you?
和他的一样
I'll have the same.
自我介绍下  我叫甘道夫
I should introduce myself. My name is Gandalf.
灰袍巫师甘道夫
Gandalf the Grey.
我听说过你
I know who you are.
碰到你真巧
Well, now, this is a fine chance.
什么风把索林·橡木盾吹来了布里
What brings Thorin Oakenshield to Bree?
我收到消息
I receive words
有人看到我父亲在登兰德荒野游荡
that my father have been seen wandering in the wilds near Dunland.
我去找过  但一无所获
I went looking, found no sign of him.
索林  很久以来
Thorin, it's been a long time since anything
瑟莱因的消息都只是谣言
but rumor was heard of Thrain.
他还活着  我敢保证
He still lives, I am sure of it.
我父亲失踪前拜访过你
My father came to see you before he went missing.
你对他说了什么
What did you say to him?
我敦促他进军艾雷博
I urged him to march upon Erebor.
集合矮人的七支大军
To gather the seven armies of dwarves.
消灭恶龙  收复孤山
To destroy the dragon and take back the Lonely Mountain.
我也要同样敦促你  去收复家园
And I would say the same to you, take back your homeland.
你不是碰巧遇到我吧  甘道夫
This is no chance meeting, is it, Gandalf?
不
No.
不是
It is not.
孤山一直困扰着我  索林
The Lonely Mountain troubles me, Thorin.
恶龙盘踞得太久
That dragon has sat there long enough.
会引来更加邪恶的力量
Sooner or later, darker minds will turn towards Erebor.
我顺绿色大道南下时  遇到了些讨厌的生物
I ran into some unsavory characters whilst travelling along Greenway.
把我当成了流浪汉
They mistook me for a vagabond.
他们肯定后悔了
I imagine they regreted that.
他们还带了个信
One of them was carrying a message.
这是黑语言[魔多语]
It is Black Speech.
-这是悬赏  -悬赏什么
- He promised as payment. - For what?
你的人头
Your head.
有人想要你死
Someone wants you dead.
索林  你不能再等了
Thorin, you could wait no longer,
你是杜林王座的继承人
you are the heir to the throne of Durin.
召集矮人军队
Unite the armies of the Dwarves.
齐心协力  去夺回艾雷博
Together you have the might and power to retake Erebor.
召集七大矮人家族的会议
Summon a meeting of the seven Dwarf families,
要求他们信守誓言
demand they stand by their oath.
七大家族的军队
The Seven Armies sworn an oath to the one
只效忠手握阿肯宝钻的人
who wields the King's Jewel, the Arkenstone.
只有帝王珍宝才能联合他们
It is the only thing that will unite them,
而且  那宝石已经被斯矛革偷走了
and in case you have forgotten, that jewel was stolen by Smaug.
如果我帮助你找回它呢
What if I were to help you reclaim it?
怎么找  宝石远在半个中土世界之外
How? The Arkenstone lies half a world away,
在那只火龙的魔掌中
buried beneath the feet of a fire-breathing dragon.
对
Yes.
所以我们需要一个盗贼
Which is why we're going to need a burglar.
12个月后
-半兽人狼群有多远  -非常近
- How close is the pack? - Too close.
只有几里格
Couple of leagues, no more.
一里格=3英里
但还有更要命的
But that's not the worst of it.
他们会嗅到我们的气味的
They will smell us, pick our scent.
现在还没  不过迟早会的
Not yet but they will do.
我们还有别的麻烦
We have another problem.
他们看见你了吗
Did they see you?
-看见了你吗  -不  不是这个
- They saw you? - No. That's not it.
我怎么说的  安静得像只老鼠
What did I tell you? Quiet as a mouse.
天生是块盗贼的料
Excellent burglar material.
听我说  都听我说话
Would you listen? Will you just listen?
我要说的是  外面还有其他东西
I'm trying to tell you there is something else out there.
它什么样子  像头熊吗
What form did it take, like a bear?
对  但更大  大得多
Yes, but bigger, much bigger.
你认识那野兽吗
You knew about this beast?
我觉得应该原路返回
I say we double back.
那会被兽人追上的
We will be run down by a pack of wolves.
有栋房子  离这不远
There is a house, it's not far from here,
可供我们躲避
where we might take refuge.
谁的房子
Whose house?
-是敌是友  -都不是
- A friend or foe? - Neither.
他也许会帮助我们  也许会杀了我们
He will help us, or, he will kill us.
我们还有其他选择吗
What choice do we have?
没有
None.
这边  快跑
This way, quickly!
走
Move!
快点
Come on.
进房子里
In the house!
快跑
Run!
快点  进去
Come on, get inside.
打开门
Open the door!
快点
Quickly.
用力推
Push!
快点
Come on!
那是什么
What is that?
我们的房主
That is our host.
他叫贝荣
His name is Beorn.
他是个变形人
And he's a skin-changer.
有时是头壮硕的黑熊
Sometimes he's a huge black bear,
有时是个高大强壮的男人
sometimes he's a great strong man.
黑熊喜怒无常  但变成人  他还是讲道理的
The bear is unpredictable, but the man can be reasoned with.
不过  他不太喜欢矮人
However, he's not over fond of Dwarves.
-他走了  -离门远一点
- He's leaving. - Come away from there!
它不正常  这都不正常
It's not natural, none of it!
他肯定被黑魔法控制了
It's obvious, he's under some dark spell.
别犯傻  那是他自己的变形术
Don't be a fool. He's under no enchantment but his own.
好了  现在  大家休息吧
All right, now. Get some sleep, all of you.
今晚你们在这儿是安全的
You'll be safe here tonight.
但愿
I hope.
现在就进攻
趁矮人渣滓睡着时杀光他们
不
那头野兽在站岗
我们要在半路上截杀他们
大军正在多尔戈多集结
主人召见你
至尊戒  驭众戒
Ash nazg durbatuluk
至尊戒  寻众戒
Ash nazg gimbatul
至尊魔戒引众戒
Ash nazg thrakatuluk
黑暗之中锁众戒
Agh burzum-ishi krimpatul
我们人数日渐增长
力量日渐增强
你来统领军队吧
橡木盾怎么办
战火将至
你说我可以取他的人头
凡人终有一死
还要追杀他们吗
博格
我有任务给你
还想喝矮人的血吗
你就是那个橡木盾
So you are the one they call Oakenshield.
告诉我  为什么亵渎者阿佐格要追杀你
Tell me, why is Azorg the Defiler hunting you?
你认识阿佐格  怎么回事
You know of Azorg. How?
我的族人最先在山中定居
My people were the first to live in the mountains.
远在兽人南下之前
Before the Orcs came down from the north.
亵渎者几乎杀光了我的家人
The Defiler killed most of my family.
只留了几个做奴隶
But some he enslaved.
不是做苦力  明白吗
Not for work, you understand?
是为了娱乐
But for sport.
他似乎觉得折磨变形人是种消遣
Caging skin-changers and torturing them seemed to amuse him.
还有像你这样的人吗
There are others like you?
曾经有很多
Once there were many.
现在呢
And now?
只剩一个了
Now there's only one.
你们要在秋天结束前抵达孤山
You need to reach the mountain before the last days of autumn.
对  在杜林之日前
Before Durin's Day falls, yes.
你们没多少时间了
You're running out of time.
所以我们必须穿过黑森林
Which is why we must go through Mirkwood.
有阴影笼罩着黑森林
A darkness lies upon that forest.
邪恶在林间滋生
Foul things creep beneath those trees.
墨瑞亚的兽人和多尔戈多的亡灵法师
There is an alliance between the Orcs of Moria
结成了同盟
and the Necromancer in Dol Guldur.
我不会冒险去那里  除非迫不得已
I would not venture there, except in great need.
我们走精灵之路  那里再安全不过
We will take the Elven road. That path is too safe.
安全
Safe?
木精灵与其他精灵不同
The Wood-elves in Mirkwood are not like their kin.
他们没那么睿智  却更加危险
They're less wise and more dangerous.
但这不重要
But it matters not.
什么意思
What do you mean?
这片土地到处都是兽人
These lands are crawling with Orcs.
他们的数量越来越多
Their numbers are growing.
你们徒步前行  永远到不了森林的
And you're on foot, you will never reach the forest alive.
我不喜欢矮人
I don't like Dwarves.
他们贪婪又盲目
They are greedy, and blind.
瞧不起他们眼中的劣等生物
Blind to the lives of those they deem lesser than their own.
但我更恨兽人
But Orcs I hate more.
你们需要什么
What do you need?
快走吧  趁着天色还早
Go now, while you have the light.
追杀你们的人就在后面
Your hunters are not far behind.
精灵之门
The Elven Gate.
这就是去往黑森林的路
Here lies our path through Mirkwood.
没有兽人的踪迹  算我们走运
No sign of the Orcs. We have luck on our side.
把马匹放走  让它们去找主人
Set the ponies loose. Let them return to their master.
这座森林好像
This forest feels...
病了
sick.
像是被疾病困扰
As if there's a disease lies upon it.
没有其他路可走了吗
Is there no way around?
除非往北走200英里  或往南走...
Not unless we go to 200 miles north, or twice that distance...
400英里
south.
阴影中有股力量蠢蠢欲动
Something moves in the shadows unseen,
躲避我们的耳目
hidden from our sight.
它的力量日渐强大
Every day it grows in strength.
小心那个亡灵法师
Beware the Necromancer.
他可不简单
He's not what he seems.
如果敌人归来了  一定要通知我
If our enemy has returned, we must know.
快去山中的戒灵坟墓
Go to the tombs in the mountains.
高丘
The High Fells.
好吧
So be it.
我还要骑马  等等
Not my horse, I need it.
你不是要离开吧
You're not leaving us?
我也是迫不得已
I will not do this unless I had to.
你变了  比尔博·巴金斯
You've changed. Bilbo Baggins.
不是离开夏尔时的那个霍比特了
And not the same Hobbit as the one who left Shire.
我本来想告诉你...
I was going to tell you...
我在半兽人的隧道里发现了一样东西
I found something in the Goblin Tunnels.
什么东西
Found what?
你发现了什么
What did you find?
我的勇气
My courage.
很好  很不错
Good. Well that's good.
你需要勇气
You need it.
我在艾雷博山前的瞭望角等你们
I'll be waiting for you at the overlook before the slopes of Erebor.
小心保管地图和钥匙
Keep the map and key safe.
不要擅自进入孤山
Do not enter the Mountain without me.
这可不是绿林
This is not the Greenwood.
森林的空气中充斥着幻象
Although the very air of the forest is heavy
侵蚀你们的意志
with illusion that'll see to enter your mind...
引你们误入歧途
and lead you astray.
误入歧途
Lead us astray?
那是什么意思
What does that mean?
必须沿着路走  不要离开
You must stay on the path, do not leave it.
否则就再也找不到路了
If you do, you'll never find it again.
不管发生什么  务必沿着路走
No matter what may come, stay on the path!
走吧  要在杜林之日的日落前赶到孤山
Come on, we must reach the mountain before the sunset on Durin's Day.
杜林之日
Durin's Day?
-走吧  -我们只有一次机会找到隐秘之门
- Let's go. - We have one chance to find the hidden door .
路往这边拐了
The path goes this way.
这边
This way.
空气  我需要空气
Air. I need air.
我的脑袋在打转  怎回事
My head, it's spinning. What's happening?
-继续走  -诺瑞
- We're moving. - Nori.
为什么停下来
Why have we stopped?
路径消失了
The path, it's disappeared.
怎么了
What's going on?
路不见了
We've lost the path.
那就找  大家一起找
Find it. All of you, look! Look for the path!
我不记得这地方  从来没见过
I don't remember this place, none of it is familiar.
在哪里
Where is it?
不知道  我们连这是哪都不知道
We do not know. We do not even know what it is.
看  烟草袋
Look, a tobacco pouch.
这森林里有矮人
There's Dwarves in these woods.
而且还是蓝山的矮人
Dwarves in the Blue Mountains no less.
这和我的烟草袋一模一样
This is exactly the same as mine.
因为就是你的
Because it is yours.
明白吗  我们在绕圈子  我们迷路了
You understand? We are going round in circles, we are lost.
我们没有迷路  我们在往东走
We're not lost, we keep heading east.
但哪面是东
But which way is the east?
我们看不见太阳
We've lost the sun.
太阳  要找到太阳
The sun, we have to find the sun.
在上面
Up there.
那是什么
What's that?
够了  都给我安静
Enough! Quiet, all of you!
有人在盯着我们
We're being watched.
我看见了湖
I, I can see a lake.
和一条河
And a river,
还有孤山
and the Lonely Mountain.
我们就快到了
We're almost there.
你们能听见吗
Can you hear me?
我知道路了
I know which way to go.
人呢
Hello?
有人吗
Hello.
不  别啊
No, come on!
赶紧吃  都跑不掉了
Eat them now, none is running.
他的皮很硬  里面肯定多汁
His hide is tough, this could be juicy inside.
杀了他
Finish it.
他还活着  你没杀掉他
He's alive, you didn't kill him.
赶紧杀了他
Kill him now!
开吃
Feast!
什么东西
What is it?
不欺负你
Fair terms, you see.
只尝一小口
Just a little taste.
什么东西  在哪儿  在哪儿
Where is it? Where is it? Where is it?
在这里
Here.
刺到我了  疼死我了
It stings, stings!
刺
Sting?
这名字不错
It's a good name.
刺叮剑
Sting.
-我没事  -比尔博在哪儿
- I'm all right. - Where's Bilbo?
-比尔博  -我在上面
- Bilbo. - I'm up here.
拉
Haul!
在哪儿  到哪儿去了  掉哪儿去了
Where is it? Where is it? Where is it?
不
No!
格罗因  奇力
Gloin! Kili!
杀光它们
Kill them all!
奇力
Kili!
是我的
Mine.
快  跟上
Come on, keep up!
别以为我不会下杀手  矮人
Do not think I will not kill you, Dwarf.
我乐意之极
It would be my pleasure.
-不  -奇力
- No! - Kili!
把你的匕首扔给我
Throw me your dagger!
快点
Quick!
你以为我会给你武器吗  矮人
Did you think I'm giving you a weapon, Dwarf?
你想错了
You're mistaken!
搜身
Search them.
还给我  这是私人物品
Hey, give it back, that's private!
这是谁  你的弟弟吗
Who is this? your brother?
那是我老婆
That is my wife!
这长得像半兽人的是谁  这么丑
And what is this horrid creature, a Goblin-mutant?
那是我家儿子  金雳
That's my wee lad, Gimli!
指环王三部曲中的矮人战士  后与莱戈拉斯成为挚友
蜘蛛都死了吗
是的  但还会有的
它们越来越放肆了
这是上古精灵宝剑
我的族人打造的
你从哪得到的
Where did you get this?
别人送的
It was given to me.
不但是个贼  还是个骗子
Not just a thief but a liar as well.
带他们走
Enwenno hain!
索林  比尔博去哪了
Thorin, where's Bilbo?
关上大门
跟你们没完
This is not the end of it!
你不来搜我的身吗
Aren't you going to search me?
我裤裆里可能什么都有哦
I could have anything down my trousers.
或是什么都没有
Or nothing.
那矮人为什么盯着你看  塔睿尔
谁知道
他倒是个挺高的矮人
你说呢
是比一般的矮人高
但还是一样丑
放弃吧
Leave it!
逃不出去的  这不是半兽人的地牢
There is no way out, this is no Orc dungeon.
这里是林地王国的牢房
These are holes of the Woodland Realm.
没有国王的恩准  谁也不出去
No one leaves here but by the King's consent.
有人觉得这是什么崇高的使命
Some imagine that a noble quest is at hand.
收复家园  消灭恶龙
A quest to reclaim a homeland, and slay a dragon.
但我觉得你们没有这么高尚
I myself suspect a more prosiac motive.
你们只能干偷鸡摸狗的勾当
Attempted burglary or something of that ilk.
你找到了进山的方法
You have found a way in.
你在找能赋予你王权的宝物
You seek that which would bestow upon you, the right to rule.
帝王珍宝
The King's Jewel.
阿肯宝钻
The Arkenstone.
在你眼中是无价之宝
It is precious to you beyond measure.
我能够理解
I understand that.
山中众多宝石  我也觊觎已久
The gems in the Mountain that I, too, desire...
白色的宝石  如同纯洁的星光
White gems, a pure starlight.
我可以帮你
I offer you my help.
请说吧
I'm listening.
我会放你们走
I would let you go,
但要把我的财宝还给我
if you but return what is mine.
公平交换
A favor for a favor.
王者之间的约定
Have my word, one king to another.
哪怕世界毁灭
I would not trust Thranduil,
我也不会相信瑟兰迪尔  这位国王的承诺
a great king to honor his words till the end of all days be upon us.
你不值得信任
You lack all honor!
我看到过你怎样对待盟友
I've seen how you treat your friends.
我们找到你
We came to you once,
饥肠辘辘  无家可归  渴求你的帮助
starving, homeless , seeking your help.
你却袖手旁观
But you turned your back.
你转身离去  让我的人民饱受煎熬
You turned away from the suffering of my people.
面对毁灭家园的地狱之火
The inferno that destroyed us.
葬身火海
Imrid amrad ursul!
不要跟我说龙火
Do not talk to me of dragon fire.
我体会过它的力量
I know its wrath and ruin.
我也斗过北方的恶龙
I have faced the great serpents of the north.
我警告过你的祖父  他的贪婪必会引来恶果
I warned your grandfather of what his greed would summon.
但他充耳不闻
But he would not listen.
你和他一样
You are just like him.
在这里待到尸骨无存吧
Stay here if you will, and rot.
100年对精灵来说  只是一瞬间
100 years is a mere blink in the life of an Elf.
我有的是耐心  我会等的
I am patient. I can wait.
-他向你提条件了吗  -提了
- Did he offer you a deal? - He did.
我唾弃了他的先祖
I told him he can go ish kakhfê ai'd dur rugnu!
还有他的族人们
Him and all his kin!
好吧
That's that, then.
那是我们唯一的希望了
The deal was our only hope.
还不是唯一的
Not our only hope.
我知道你在那
I know you're there.
为什么要在阴影中徘徊
Why do you linger in the shadows?
我是来向您报告的
I was coming to report to you.
我两日前就下令要你摧毁那个巢穴了吧
I thought I ordered that nest to be destroyed not 2 moons past.
森林已经扫荡过了  主上
We cleared the forest as ordered, my lord.
但还有蜘蛛不断从南边涌入
But more spiders keep coming up from the south.
他们在多尔戈多的废墟中繁殖
They are spawning in the ruins of Dol Guldur.
如果能从源头上扼制住他们
If we could kill them at their source...
他们的堡垒远在边界之外
The fortress lies beyond our borders.
避免邪恶生物侵入我们的领土
Keep our lands clear of those foul creatures.
这才是你的工作
That is your task.
就算赶跑了又怎样
And when we drive them off? What then?
他们难道不会跑到其他地方去吗
Will they not spread to other lands?
其他地方不关我的事
Other lands are not my concern.
外面的世界潮起潮落
Fortunes of the world will rise and fall.
只有我们的国度永在
But here in this kingdom, we will endure.
莱戈拉斯说你今天非常英勇
Legolas said you fought well today.
他对你是渐生好感
He's grown very fond of you.
我向您保证  主上
I assure you, my lord.
在他眼里  我只不过是个卫队长
Legolas thinks of me as no more than a captain of the guard.
也许以前是
Perhaps he did once.
现在可不一定了
Now I'm not so sure.
我想您不会允许自己的儿子
I do not think you would allow your son
对出身卑微的木精灵有好感吧
to pledge himself to a lowly Silvan Elf.
没错  我不会允许
No, you're right. I would not.
但他还是很在乎你
Still, he cares about you.
没有希望  就不要让他幻想
Do not give him hope where there is none.
门口有人守卫
他们人数不足  跟我来
归来吧  innikh dê
你手里的那枚石头是什么
The stone in your hand, what is it?
是个护身符
It is a talisman.
上面刻着强大的咒语
A powerful spell lies upon it,
只要不是矮人  看到咒语
if any but a Dwarf reads the runes on this stone...
就会受到永恒的诅咒
They will be forever cursed.
也没准
Or not.
信则灵  不信则不灵
Depending on whether you believe.
这种东西只是个象征
This kind of thing is just a token.
符文石
A rune stone.
我妈妈给我的  好让我记得承诺
My mother gave it to me so I'd remember my promise.
什么承诺
What promise?
我会回到她身边
That I would come back to her.
她很担心
She worries.
她觉得我很鲁莽
She thinks I'm reckless.
是吗
Are you?
好盛大的宴会
Sounds like quite a party having out there.
那是星光盛宴
It is mereth en gilith.
在星光下的晚宴
The feast of starlight.
精灵认为光都是神圣的
All light is sacred to the Eldar.
但木精灵最爱的是星光
But Wood Elves love best for light of the stars.
我一直觉得星光是清冷的
I always thought it is a cold light.
遥不可及
Remote and far away.
那是回忆
It is memory.
纯洁宝贵
Precious and pure.
像你的承诺一样
Like your promise.
我上去过几次
I have walked there sometimes.
森林上面  深入夜色
Beyond the forest and up into the night.
远远地看着整个世界
I have seen the world full away.
夜空中充满了白色的光辉
And the white light forever fill the air.
我见过一次焰月
I saw fire moon once.
在登兰德附近的路上
The roads of the path near Dunland.
巨大的月亮  火红金灿的光芒
Huge, red and golden it was, filled the sky.
我们当时护送一批梅督林的商人
We were an escort for some merchants in Mindolluin,
他们用银器换皮毛
they were trading in silver work for furs.
我们沿着绿色大道南下
We took the Greenway south.
山一直在我们左侧
Keeping the mountain to our left.
日暮之后
At the end of the day,
一轮巨大的焰月  照亮我们的路
you see huge fire moon lighting our path.
我们的酒快喝完了
We're running out of drink.
这些空酒桶早就该送回埃加洛斯了
These empty barrels should be sent back to Esgaroth hours ago.
驳船工肯定在等了
Bargeman would be waiting for them.
随你怎么说
Say what you like,
咱的臭脾气国王藏的美酒不能放过
but the ill-tempered king has this excellent, tasty wine.
-来吧  罗斯 尝一下  -我还要看管矮人呢
- Come on, Ross, try it. - I have the Dwarves in my charge.
都被锁起来了  还能跑到哪去
They're locked up, where can they go?
我敢打赌就要日出了  肯定快到黎明了
I'll wager the sun is on the rise. Must be nearly dawn.
我们是不是永远都到不了孤山了
We never gonna reach the mountain, are we?
关在这里怎么去孤山
Not stuck in here, you know?
比尔博
Bilbo.
附近有卫兵
There are guards nearby.
这是什么
What's this?
你先走
You first.
-欧瑞  -不是那边  在下面  跟我来
- Ori. - Not that way. Down here, follow me!
这边
This way.
-快来  -我们居然跑到酒窖来了
- Come. - I don't believe we're in the cellars!
你应该带我们找出去的路
You're supposed to be leading us out now for the road!
我脑子清楚得很
I know what I'm doing.
这边
This way.
所有人  快进酒桶  快点
Everyone, climb into the barrels, quickly!
你疯了吗  他们会发现我们的
Are you mad? They'll find us.
不  不  不会的  我保证
No, no, they won't. I promise you!
拜托  一定要相信我
Please, please, you must trust me!
按他说的做
Do as he says.
我们现在该干什么
What do we do now?
屏住呼吸
Hold your breath.
屏住呼吸  什么意思
Hold my breath? What do you mean?
钥匙在谁手里
Where is the keeper of the keys?
欢迎  巴金斯大师
Welcome, Master Baggins.
快点  出发了
Come on, let's go.
抓稳了
Hold on!
比尔博
Bilbo!
坚持住
Hang on.
不  救命啊
No. Help!
关闸门
不要
No!
小心
Watch out!
全杀光
去桥上
Get on to the bridge!
奇力
Kili?
杀了她  杀了那个母精灵
追上他们
奇力
Kili?
诺瑞
Nori!
一起来
Come along!
邦伯
Bombur!
等等
不要杀他
追上去  拦住他们
是你啊
Oh, it's you.
为什么要我来这  甘道夫
Why am I here, Gandalf?
相信我  瑞达加斯特
Trust me, Radagast.
我不会无缘无故叫你来的
I would not have called you here without a good reason.
这里不适合见面
This is not a nice place to meet.
的确不适合
No. It is not.
这里都是黑魔法  甘道夫
These are dark spells, Gandalf.
怨气很重  古老的黑魔法
Old, and full of hate.
这里埋的是谁
Who's buried here?
就算他有名字  也早被人遗忘了
If he had name, it's long since been lost.
人们只会记得他是恶魔的仆从
He would have been known only as a servant of evil.
九个戒灵之一
One of nine.
为什么是现在  甘道夫  我不明白
Why now, Gandalf? I don't understand.
戒灵被召唤到了多尔戈多
The Ring-wraiths is summoned to Dol Guldur.
但不可能是亡灵法师
But it can not be the Necromancer.
人类不可能召唤出这么邪恶的东西
A human sorcerer could not summon such evil.
谁说他是人类
Who said it was human?
九个戒灵只效忠一人
The Nine only answer to one master.
我们没有注意到  瑞达加斯特
We've been blind, Radagast.
敌人趁我们不备  卷土重来了
And in our blindness the enemy has returned.
他在召集他的仆从
He's summoning his servants.
亵渎者阿佐格可不是普通的猎手
Azorg the Defiler is no ordinary hunter.
他是个指挥官  军团指挥官
He's a commander, a commander of legions.
敌人要发动战争
The enemy is preparing for war.
从东边起  他盯上了孤山
It will begin in the east. His mind is set upon that mountain.
你要去哪
Where are you going?
-和其他人汇合  -甘道夫
- To rejoin the others. - Gandalf.
是我牵的头  我不能抛弃他们
I started this, I can not forsake them.
他们危在旦夕了
They are in grave danger.
如果你说的是真的
If what you say is true...
整个世界都危在旦夕了
the world is in grave danger.
他藏在堡垒中积蓄力量
The power in that fortress will only grow stronger.
你想让我把朋友们抛到一旁
You want me to cast my friends aside.
-还有人追吗  -我看没有了
- Anything behind us? - Not that I can see.
应该甩掉兽人了
I think we've outrun the Orcs.
只能逃一时
Not for long.
这里水流太缓
We've lost the current.
大家上岸  来吧  我们走
Make for the shore. Come on, let's go.
加油
Come on.
我没事  小伤而已
I'm fine. It's nothing.
-走起来  -奇力受伤了  腿需要包扎
- On your feet. - Kili's wounded, his leg needs binding.
有一队兽人跟在我们后面  得赶紧走了
There's an Orc pack on our tail. We keep moving.
-去哪  -去孤山  我们很近了
- To where? - To the mountain, we're so close.
中间隔着一座湖呢
A lake lies between us and that mountain.
我们没有办法渡湖
We have no way to cross it.
-那我们就绕过去  -兽人肯定会追上来
- So then we go arround. - The Orcs'll run us down, as sure as daylight.
我们也没有防身的武器
We have no weapon to defend ourselves.
快包扎他的腿  给你两分钟时间
Bind his legs quickly. You have 2 minutes.
我不会再手下留情了
Do it again...and you're dead.
不好意思  你是从长湖城来的
Excuse me, but, um...you're from Lake-town,
我没看错吧
if I'm not mistaken?
那边的驳船
That barge over there,
有没有可能租给我们
is it available for hire by any chance?
你为什么觉得我会帮你们
What makes you think I would help you?
从靴子看  你过的日子挺苦
Those boots have seen better days.
从大衣看也是
As has that coat.
想必你还要养家糊口吧
No doubt you have some hungry mouths to feed.
几个孩子
How many bearings?
一个男孩两个女孩
A boy and two girls.
我猜你妻子肯定是个大美人
And your wife, I imagine she's a beauty.
对  曾经是
Aye, she was.
对不起  我不是故意的
I'm sorry, I didn't mean to...
得了  得了  客套个什么劲
Come on, come on. Enough for the niceties!
你着什么急
What's your hurry?
关你什么事
What's it to you?
我想知道你们是什么人
I would like to know who you are.
又在这里做些什么事情
And what you are doing in these lands.
我们是从蓝山来的商人
We are simple merchants from the Blue Mountains.
要去铁丘陵走亲戚
Journeying to see our kin in the Iron Hills.
你们说是普通商人
Simple merchants you say.
我们需要食物  补给和武器
We need food, supplies, weapons.
你能帮忙吗
Can you help us?
我知道这些木桶是哪来的
I know where these barrels came from.
怎么了
What of it?
我不知道你们和精灵之间发生了什么
I don't know what business you had with the Elves.
但我觉得结果不太妙
But I don't think it ended well.
除非城主带路  没有人进得了长湖城
No one enters Lake-town but by lead of The Master.
他的收入全靠和林地王国的交易
All his wealth comes from trades with the Woodland Realm.
他肯定会把你们扔进牢房
He would see you in irons
不敢招惹瑟兰迪尔国王
before risking the wraith of king Thranduil.
我打赌肯定有悄悄进城的方法
I'll wager there are ways to enter that town unseen.
对
Aye.
但要有个走私贩帮忙
But for that, you would need a smuggler.
我们会付钱的  双倍
For which we will pay, double.
邪恶就是如此愚蠢
Such is the nature of evil.
即使遍布中土  依旧闭塞盲目
Out there in the vast ignorance of the world it festers and spreads.
有阴影在黑暗中成长
A shadow that grows in the dark.
那恶灵昼夜不休
A sleepless malice
如夜幕一般黑暗
as black as the oncoming wall of night.
之前是这样  以后也永远会这样
So it ever was. So will it always be.
最后  所有的邪恶都会现身
In time, all foul things come forth.
你们在追杀13个矮人
You were tracking a company of 13 Dwarves.
为什么
Why?
不是13个
Not 13.
不再是了
Not any more.
那个年轻人  黑头发的弓箭手
The young one, the black-haired archer.
他中了魔窟的箭
We stuck him of a Morgul shaft.
毒液渗入血液  他活不长了
Poison is in his blood, he'll be choking on it soon.
回答问题  渣滓
Answer the question, filth.
狗没有权利问我问题  母精灵
最好别惹怒她
I would not antagonize her.
你喜欢杀戮吗  兽人
You like killing things, Orc?
你喜欢死亡吗
You like death?
那就让你尝尝死亡的滋味
Then let me give it to you!
够了
塔睿尔  走开
马上
我不在乎矮人的死活  回答我的问题
I do not care about one dead Dwarf. Answer the question.
没什么好害怕的
You have nothing to fear.
把知道的都说出来  我就放你自由
Tell us what you know and I will set you free.
有人要杀死他们  为什么
You had orders to kill them, Why?
索林·橡木盾对你们有什么用
What is Thorin Oakenshield to you?
那个矮冬瓜永远别想当国王
The Dwarf runt will never be king.
国王吗  没有山下之王
King? There's no King Under the Mountain.
将来也不会有  只要那头龙还活着
Nor will there ever be. None would they enter Erebor
没人进得去艾雷博
whilst the dragon lives.
你知道什么
You know nothing.
你们的世界将化为火海
Your world will burn.
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
快说
Speak!
我们的时代又回来了
Our time has come again.
我的主人效忠于他
My master serves the One.
现在明白了吧  精灵  死亡就要到来了
Do you understand now, Elfling? Death is upon you.
战火就要蔓延到这了
The flames of war are upon you.
你为什么这么做
Why did you do that?
你说过要放他自由
You promised to set him free.
我照做了
And I did.
我解放了他那卑鄙的头颅
I freed his wretched head from his miserable shoulders.
这兽人嘴里还能套出话来
There was more the Orc could tell us.
我觉得没什么价值了
There was nothing more he could tell me.
他说的战火是什么意思
What did he mean by the flames of war?
他们要使用什么武器
It means they intend to unleash a weapon
这武器强大到可以毁灭一切
so great it will destroy all before it.
边境  道路和河流的守卫通通加倍
I want the watch doubled at our borders, all roads, all rivers.
一有动静  立即禀报
Nothing moves that I hear of it.
严禁任何人进出
No one enters this kingdom, and no one leaves it.
关闭城门
国王下令封城
那塔睿尔怎么办
她怎么了
她带着弓箭和匕首
跑进森林里去了
还没有回来
矮人的血
他们经过这里
还有另一股味道
是人肉
他们找到渡湖的方法了
小心点
Watch out!
你干什么  想淹死我们吗
What are you trying to do? Drown us?
这片水域生养了我  矮人老爷
I was born and bred on these waters , master Dwarf.
就算我想淹死你们  也不会选这里
If I wanted to drown you, I would not do it here.
我受够这个长湖城的滑头了
Oh, I've had enough of this slippy lake-man.
要我说直接丢掉他  甩了他
I say we throw him over the sail and then we dump him.
巴德  他叫巴德
Bard, his name is Bard.
你怎么知道的
How do you know?
我问的
Um, I asked him.
我才不管他叫什么  我不喜欢他
I don't care what he calls himself, I don't like him.
我们不需要喜欢他  付钱给他就行
We do not have to like him. We simply have to pay him.
来吧伙计  钱都拿出来
Come now lads, turn out your pockets.
我们怎么知道他不会背叛我们
How do we know he won't betray us?
不知道
We don't.
还有个大问题
There's um, still a big problem.
还差10枚银币
We're 10 coins short.
葛罗音  快点  把你的钱拿出来
Gloin, come on. Give us what you have.
找我干什么
Don't look to me.
这次冒险弄得我倾家荡产
I've been bled dry by this venture.
一点回报都没见到
What have I seen from my investment?
什么都没有  只有痛苦和悲伤
Naught but misery and grief and...
老天爷啊
Bless my beard.
拿去  全都拿走
Take it, take all of it.
钱呢  快点给我
The money, quick, give it to me.
拿到供给之后自然会付你钱
We will pay you when we get our provisions,
否则不行
but not before.
不想被关进大牢  就听我的
If you value your freedom, you'll do as I say.
前面有守卫
There are guards ahead.
他在干什么
What's he doing?
他在和什么人说话
He's talking to someone.
还对着我们指指点点
He's pointing right at us.
现在握起手来了
Now they're shaking hands.
什么
What?
这个坏人
The villain!
他把我们卖了
He's selling us out.
安静
Quiet!
马上到城门关了
We're approaching the tollgate.
停船  货物检查  请出示文书
Halt. Goods inspection. Papers, please.
原来是你啊  巴德
Oh, it's you, Bard.
早上好  珀西
Morning, Percy.
有什么要申报的吗
Anything to declare?
没有  我又累又冷  想赶紧回家
Nothing, that I am cold and tired, and ready for home.
我也是
You and me both.
给你  没问题了
Here we are, all in order.
别着急
Not so fast.
从林地王国托运回来的空木桶
Consignment of empty barrels from the Woodland Realm.
怎么不是空的呢
Only, they are not empty,
巴德
are they, Bard?
没记错的话  你的执照是驳船工
If I recall correctly. Your licensed as a bargeman.
而不是渔夫
Not a fisherman.
不关你的事
That's none of your business!
错了  这关城主的事  也就是我的事
Wrong. It's the Master's business, which makes it my business.
拜托  埃弗雷德  讲点情理  城民等着吃饭呢
Oh, come on, Alfred, Have a heart. People need to eat!
这些鱼是非法的
These fish are illegal.
-把桶清空  -快点
- Empty the barrels over the side. - You heard him.
倒进河里
In the canal.
快点
Come on.
镇上的人民在挨饿
Folks in this town are struggling.
日子艰难  食物又少
Times are hard, food is scarce.
跟我有什么关系
That's not my problem.
如果人们听说城主把鱼扔进湖里
And when the people hear their Master's dumping the fish in the lake,
掀起暴动的话
when the rioting starts,
跟你有关系了吗
Will it be your problem, then?
住手
Stop!
充当人民英雄吗  巴德  平民保护神
Ever the people's champion, aye, Bard? Protector of the common folk.
他们不会一直支持你的  船夫
You might have their favor now, bargeman. But it won't last.
把门打开
Raise the gate.
别忘了  城主盯着你呢
The Master has his eye on you, you do well to remember.
我们知道你住哪里
We know where you live.
地方这么小  埃弗雷德  大家可都知根知底
It's a small town, Alfred. Everyone knows where everyone lives.
外面的动静很大
All these talks of civil are unrest.
有人在煽风点火  大人
Someone's been stirring the pot, Sire.
痛风了吗  大人
Gout playing ox, Sire?
是潮气  肯定是潮气  给我弄点白兰地
It's the damp, it's the only possible explanation. Get me a brandy.
大人  民众的情绪让人不快
The mood of the people, sire, is turning ugly.
平民就这样  埃弗雷德  让人不愉快
They're commoners, Alfred. They've always been ugly.
这地方到处是鱼腥臭气  又不怪我
It's not my fault that they live in a place that stinks of fish oil and tar.
工作  房屋
Jobs, shelter,
食物  只有这点追求
food, that's all they ever plead about.
大人  肯定有人在幕后指使
It is my belief, sire, that they've been led on by trouble makers.
那就给我找出来  逮捕他们
Then we must find these trouble makers, and arrest them.
我也是这么想的  大人
My thoughts exactly, sire.
改革的言论给我压下去
And all these talks of change must be supressed.
绝对不能让造反的人聚在一起  制造言论
What a fault to let the rebel banded together and start making noises.
搞不好他们还要问责  成立委员会
The next thing you know, they'll start asking questions, forming commities...
发起调查
launching inquiries.
旧的不去  新的不来
Out with the old, in with the new.
什么
What?
我一直都在这么说  大人
That's what I've been saying, sire.
还有传言说要选举
There's even talk of election.
选举  真荒唐  我绝不允许
Election? It's absurd. I won't stand for it.
他们不需要您允许吧  大人
I don't think they'll ask you to stand, sire.
这些强盗  忘恩负义  还想造反
Sackers, ingrates, rebel-rousers.
谁敢质疑我的权威
Who would have the nerve to question my authority!
谁敢  谁
Who would dare? Who...
巴德
Bard.
绝对没错  幕后黑手就是这个船夫
You mark my words, that trouble-making bargeman is behind all this.
别碰我
Get your hands off me.
你没见过他们  他们没来过这里
You didn't see them. They were never here.
鱼送你了
Fish you can have for nothing.
跟上我
Follow me.
爸  我们的房子被监视了
Da, our house, it's being watched.
告诉城主我今天办完事了
You can tell the Master I'm done for the day.
爸
Da.
你去哪了
Where have you been?
爸爸  你回来了  我好担心
Father, there you are! I was worried.
好  贝恩  叫他们出来
Yes. Bain, get them in.
要是你跟别人说  我就把你的胳膊拧下来
If you speak of this to anyone. I'll rip your arms off.
别碰我
Off.
在那边
Out there.
爸  为什么有矮人从厕所里爬出来
Da, why are the Dwarves climbing out from our toilet?
他们能带来好运吗
Will they bring us luck?
可能不是很合身  但是保暖
They may not be the best fit, but they'll keep you warm.
谢谢
Thank you.
矮人风弩
The Dwarvish Windlass.
你像是见了鬼魂一样
You look like you've seen a ghost.
没错  上次见到这武器
Yes. The last time we saw such a weapon,
河谷城化为了灰烬
a city was on fire.
那天巨龙袭来
It was the day the dragon came.
斯矛革摧毁了河谷城
The day that Smaug destroyed Dale.
城主吉利恩
Girion, the Lord of the city.
集结弓箭手射击巨龙
Rallied his bowman to fire upon the beast.
但龙皮无比坚固  牢不可破
But a dragon's hide is tough. Tougher than the strongest armor.
只有风弩射出的黑箭能够刺穿
Only a black arrow fired from a Windlass would pierce the dragon hide.
这种箭本就寥寥无几
And few of those arrows were ever made.
吉利恩背水一战时  仅剩数支
The store was running low when Girion made his last stand.
哪怕他能射中一箭
Had the aim of men been true that day...
也不会落到这步田地
much would've been different.
难道你当时在场
You speak as if you were there?
所有矮人都知道这个故事
All Dwarves know the tale.
那你应该知道吉利恩击中了巨龙
And you would know that Girion hit the dragon?
射落了左翼的一块鳞片
It loosened the scale on the left wing
再补一箭就能杀死那怪物
one more shot he would have killed the beast.
不过是童话而已  孩子  只是童话
That's fairy story, lad. Nothing more.
你收了钱
You took all our money.
武器在哪里
Where are the weapons?
等着
Wait here.
明天是最后一个秋日
Tomorrow begins our last day of autumn.
后天便是杜林之日
Durin's day falls the morning after next.
必须在那之前赶到孤山
We must reach the mountain before then.
如果不能呢
And if we do not?
如果那之前找不到隐秘之门呢
If we fail to find the hidden door before that time?
那计划就全落空了
Then this quest has been for nothing.
这是什么
What is this?
钩矛
Pike hook.
旧鱼叉改的
Made from an old harpoon.
这个呢
And this?
我们叫它鹤嘴锄  改进过的铁匠锤
A crowbill, we call it. Expansion from smittys hammer.
虽然上手很重
It's heavy in hand, I grant.
但需要保命时  也能凑合着用
But in defense of your life, these will serve you better than none.
我们买的是武器
We paid you for weapons.
铁铸黑鞘的宝剑
Iron forged, swords of dark sheath.
这是开玩笑
It's a joke.
这是军械库外最好的武器了
You won't find better outside the city armory.
铁铸的兵器都锁在军械库里
All iron-forged weapons are held there and locked in key.
索林
Thorin.
拿着这些走吧
Why not take his offer and go?
更差的兵器我都用过  你不也是
I've made do with less. So have you.
我们现在就走
I say we leave now.
你们哪都不能去
You're not going anywhere.
你看到什么了
What did you see?
全城的眼线  乃至狼狗都盯着这里
There are spies watching this house and probably every wolf and dog in town.
必须等到傍晚
You must wait until nightfall.
索林
Thorin.
爸
Da?
别让他们出门
Don't let them leave.
我还当你是兽人
如果我是兽人
你早就死了
不要一个人追杀30个兽人
You can not hunt 30 orcs on your own.
可我不是一个人
But I'm not on my own.
你知道我要跟来
You knew I would come?
国王很愤怒  塔睿尔
The king is angry, Tauriel.
600年来  我父亲一直保护你  宠爱你
For 600 years, my father has protected you, favored you.
你却违抗了他的命令
You defied his orders.
辜负了他的信任
You betrayed his trust.
跟我回去
他会原谅你的
但我不会
如果跟你回去  我不会原谅自己
国王从未准许兽人入境
The king has never let Orcs fill from outlands.
这次却纵容他们穿越边境
But he would let this Orc pack cross our borders
追杀我们的犯人
and kill our prisoners.
-我们不该插手  -怎么不该插手
- It is not our fight. - It is our fight.
他们不会善罢甘休  这是在助长邪恶
It will not end here. With every victory this evil will grow.
如果你父亲一意孤行  我们袖手旁观
If your father has his way, we would do nothing.
我们只能躲在城墙后  不见天日
We will hide within our walls, live our lives away from light.
任由黑暗侵袭
And let the darkness descend.
我们不是中土世界的一员吗
Are we not a part of this world?
朋友  怎么能让邪恶力量比我们强大
Tell me mellon, when did we let evil become stronger than us?
你好  巴德  你在找什么
Hello, Bard. What you after?
有一条旧挂毯  上哪去了
There was a tapestry, an old one. Where has it gone?
什么旧挂毯
What tapestry are you talking about?
这条
This one.
告诉你  他们是矮人  凭空出现的
They were Dwarves, I tell you. Appeared out of nowhere.
满脸胡子  眯缝眼  从来没见过
Full-beards, pierced eyes. I've never seen the like.
矮人在这做什么
What are Dwarves doing in these parts?
是预言
It's the prophecy.
-预言  -杜林后人的预言
- Prophecy? -Prophecy of Durin's folk.
预言
Prophecy?
Prophecy.
那些传说可能成真了
The old tales may come true.
大笔财宝
Vast hordes of treasure?
是真的吗
Can it really be true?
银泉之主回归了吗
Has the Lord of the silver fountains returned?
银泉之主  刻石之王
The lord of the silver fountains. The king of carven stone.
山下之王
The King Beneath the Mountain.
将重回宝座
Shall come into his own.
人民欢庆山下之王的回归
And the bell shall ring in gladness at the Mountain King's return.
但一切必以悲剧收场
But all shall fail in sadness,
湖水闪耀  战火重燃
and the lake will shine and burn.
-爸  我想阻止他们  -他们走了多久
- Da, I tried to stopped them... - How long have they been gone?
拿到武器  直接去孤山
As soon we have the weapons we make straight for the Mountain.
快  快  快
Go, go, go.
你还好吗
You all right?
撑得住
I can manage.
我们赶紧走吧
Let's just get out of here.
快跑
Run!
这什么意思
What is the meaning of this?
抓到他们在偷武器  大人
We caught them stealing weapon, sire.
这是全民公敌呀
Enemies of the state, em?
看样子是群下贱的佣兵  大人
A disgrace bunch of mercenaries, if ever there were, Sire.
住嘴
Hold your tongue!
你不知道你在跟谁讲话
You do not know to whom you speak.
这哪是什么犯罪  他是索林
This is no common criminal! This is Thorin,
瑟罗尔的后人  瑟莱因之子
son of Thrain, son of Thror!
我们是艾雷博的矮人
We are the Dwarves of Erebor.
我们来收复故土
We have come to reclaim our homeland.
我还记得这镇子昔日的辉煌
I remember this town in the great days of old.
码头停满了船舶
Fleets of boats laid at the harbor,
满载丝绸和珠宝
filled with silks and fine gems.
这里不是被人遗忘的湖边小城
This was no forsaken town on a lake.
这里曾是北方的贸易中心
This was the center of all trade of the North.
我要重现往日的辉煌
I would see those days return,
点亮矮人的熔炉
I would relive the great forges of Dwarves,
让艾雷博的商队
send wealth and riches flowing once more...
载满财富接踵而来
from the hordes of Erebor!
你只会带来死亡
Death, that is what you will bring upon us.
龙火和毁灭
Dragon fire and ruin.
吵醒了那怪物  我们就全完了
If you awaken that beast, it will destroy us all.
你们可以听他劝阻  不过我保证
You can listen to this nay-sayer, but I promise you this:
如果成功
If we succeed,
孤山的财富大家可以一起分享
all will share in the wealth of the Mountain.
到手的财富  可以让十个埃加洛斯重现辉煌
You will have enough gold, to rebuild Esgaroth 10 times over.
所有人  听我说  听好
All of you, listen to me! You must listen!
你们忘记河谷城的事了吗
Have you forgotten what happened in Dale?
忘记葬身火海的百姓了吗
Have you forgotten of those who died in firestorm?
都是为了什么
And for what purpose?
为了山下之王盲目的野心
The blind ambition of a Mountain King.
贪婪蒙蔽了他的双眼  他心里只有欲望
So riven by greed, he can not see beyond his own desire!
等一等  我们每个人
No, no. We must not, any of us,
都不要急着横加指责
be too quick to lay blame.
不要忘了  吉利恩
Let us not forget, that it was Girion,
河谷城主  你的先人
Lord of Dale, your ancestor,
没能杀死那怪物
who failed to kill the beast.
没错  大人  我们都知道这个故事
It's true, sire. We all know the story.
他射了一箭又一箭  却全部射偏
Arrow after arrow he shot, each one missing its mark.
你无权
You have no right,
无权进入孤山
no right to enter that mountain.
只有我有权利
I have the only right.
请问长湖城主
I speak to the Master of the men of the lake.
您愿意见证预言成真吗
Will you see the prophecy fulfilled?
愿意
Will you...
分享我们的无尽财富吗
share in the great wealth of our people?
您怎么说
What say you?
我要说  欢迎
I say unto you, welcome!
请平身  欢迎山下之王
Welcome and rise! Welcome, King under the mountain!
你知道我们少一个人吧
You do know we have one short?
-比弗在哪  -他不在也不要管他
- Where's Bifur? - He's not here, we leave him behind.
想在日落前找到门  只能这么做
You'll have to, if you were to find the door before nightfall.
我们拖不起了
We can risk no more delays.
你不能去
Not you.
今天要全力赶路  你会拖慢我们的
We must travel with speed. You'll slow us down.
你在说什么呢  我要跟你们走
What are you talking about? I'm coming with you.
不
No.
舅舅  我一定要看着那门打开
Uncle, I must be there when that door is open.
我们一定要一起仰望先祖的大厅  索林
When we first look upon the halls of our fathers, Thorin...
奇力  留下
Kili, stay here,
休息  痊愈后来找我们
rest, join us when you're healed.
我来陪这孩子
I'll stay with the lad
我的职责就是照顾伤员
my duty lies with the wounded.
舅舅
Uncle.
我们是听着孤山的故事长大的
We grew up with the tales of the Mountain, tales you told us.
不要剥夺他的梦想
You can't take that away from him.
-奇力  -我可以背着他
- Kili. - I will carry him if I must!
等你坐上王位  就能理解了
One day you will be king and you will understand.
不能因为一个矮人耽搁了远征
I cannot risk the fate of this quest for the sake of one Dwarf.
哪怕是我的亲人
Not even my own kin.
菲力  别犯傻  你跟大家在一起
Fili, don't be a fool. You belong with the company.
我要和弟弟在一起
I belong with my brother.
难道要出发了吗
By my beard, is that the time!
祝你们好运
Good fortune to all!
让开
Move.
不
No.
你们也错过开船了吗
Did you miss the boarders as well?
奇力  奇力
Kili, Kili!
不  我受够矮人了  走开
No. I'm done with Dwarves, go away.
别  别  别  没人肯帮我们
No, no, no. No one will help us.
奇力病了
Kili's sick.
是重病
He's very sick.
这是哪
What is this place?
曾经的河谷城  现在只是一片废墟
For once the city of Dale. Now it is a ruin.
斯矛革留下的荒原
The desolation of Smaug.
马上到正午了
The sun will soon reach midday.
必须在日落前找到进入孤山的隐秘之门
We must find the hidden door into the Mountain before it sets.
-这边  -等等
- This way. - Wait.
这里是瞭望角吗
Is this the overlook?
甘道夫说无论如何  都要在这等...
Gandalf said to meet him here on no account of what you hear or...
你见到他了吗  来不及等他了
Do you see him? We have no time to wait upon a wizard.
我们只能靠自己了
We're on our own.
来吧
Come.
多尔戈多  巫师之山
Dol Guldur, the hill of sorcerer.
看样子废弃已久了
It looks completely abandoned.
像是故意的
As it is meant to.
这是障眼法
A spell of concealment lies over this place.
敌人应该不想现出真身
Which means our enemies are not yet ready to reveal himself.
他还没恢复元气
He has not regained his full strength.
瑞达加斯特  给盖拉德丽尔女王送个信
Radagast, I need you to carry a message to the Lady Galadriel.
告诉她  要逼他行动了
Tell her, we must force his hand.
你什么意思
What do you mean?
我独自进去  千万不要跟着我
I'm going in alone. On no account come after me.
-你保证吗  -保证  保证
- Do I have your word? - Yes, yes, yes.
等等  甘道夫
Wait, Gandalf.
如果是个陷阱呢
What if it's a trap?
转过身去  不要回来
Turn around and do not come back.
肯定是陷阱
It's undoubtly a trap.
藏身于此的恶灵
速速现身
现出原形
藏身于此的恶灵
Cé ná ulco sís nurtaina…
速速现身
I ettuluvas caninye!
巫师来了
速速现身
I ettuluvas caninye!
巫师来了
他在施咒
他会找到我们的
那就让他找
-找到了吗  -没有
- Anything? - Nothing!
如果地图没问题  隐秘之门应该就在头顶
If the map is true, the hidden door is hidden right above us.
在那
Up here!
你眼神真锐利  巴金斯大师
You have keen eyes, Master Baggins.
肯定是这里了
This must be it.
隐秘之门
The hidden door.
那些质疑我们的人  后悔去吧
That all those who doubted us, rue this day!
我们有钥匙
Aye, we have a key.
所以应该有个锁孔
This means that somewhere, there is a keyhole.
杜林之日  落日余晖
The last light of Durin's Day...
锁孔即现
will shine upon the keyhole.
太阳要下山了  快点
We're losing the light, come on.
别乱踢  我听不到了
Be quiet! We can't hear when you're thumping!
找不到
Can't find it.
不在这
It's not here!
这里
Here!
砸开它
Wreck it down!
加油
Come on.
肯定能打开
It has to break.
没用  门锁上了
It's no good, the door is sealed.
不能用蛮力打开
Can't be opened by force.
有强力的魔法保护着
There is powerful magic on it.
不
No.
杜林之日  落日余晖
The last light of Durin's Day...
锁孔即现
will shine upon the keyhole.
就是这么说的
That what it says.
我们少了什么
What did we miss?
-巴林  -没有太阳光了
- Balin. - We've lost the light.
没有办法了
There's no more to be done.
我们只有那一次机会
We have but one chance.
过来吧  小伙子们  结束了
Come over here, lads. It's over.
等一下  怎么
Wait a minute, what...
他们去哪
Where are they going?
怎么能现在放弃
You can't give up now.
好吧
Fine.
不能现在放弃
You can't give up now.
画眉击门
Last light, the grey stone.
倚灰岩立
When the thrush nods.
杜林之日
The setting sun.
落日余晖  锁孔即现
And the last light of Durin's Day will shine...
落日余晖
The last light.
余晖
Last light.
这才是余晖
And the last light...
锁眼在那  回来
The keyhole! Come back!
回来  是月光  最后一轮秋月
Come back! It's the moon! The last moon of autumn!
钥匙呢  钥匙
Where's the key, where's the key? Where's the...
就在  附近
It was...here. It was here.
就在
It was just...
艾雷博
Erebor.
索林
Thorin.
我认得这墙
I know these walls.
这墙壁
These walls...
这岩石
The stone...
记得吗  巴林
You remember, Balin?
耀满金光的房间
Chambers filled with golden light.
记得
I remember.
此下即是杜林后人的七代王国
Herein lies the seventh kingdom of Durin's folk.
愿崇山之心团结中土矮人
May the Heart of the Mountain unite all Dwarves
保卫家园
in defense of this home.
矮人王座
The throne of the king.
再上面呢
And what's that above it?
阿肯宝钻
The Arkenstone.
Arkenstone.
-是什么  -那个  盗贼大师
- And what's that? - That, master burglar...
是你此行的使命
is why you are here.
-做点什么啊  -我需要草药
- Can you not do something? - I need herbs.
能退烧的草药
Something to bring down this fever.
有龙葵  解热草
I have nightshade, fever fuel.
指环王第一部中阿拉贡用来给弗罗多疗伤的草药
没用  王叶草有吗
They're no use to me. Do you have any kingsfoil?
没有  那是杂草  喂猪用的
No, it's a weed. We feed it to the pigs.
喂猪  杂草  对了
Pigs? Weed, right.
稍等
Don't move.
你们要我去找宝钻
Do you want me to find the jewel?
白色的  大钻石  是的
A large white jewel, yes.
又白又大吗  底下应该不少吧
That's it? Only I imagine there's quite a few down there.
阿肯宝钻是独一无二的
There is only one Arkenstone.
你一眼就能认出
You'll know it when you see it.
很好
Right.
实话说  孩子  我也不知道底下有什么
In truth, lad. I do not know what you'll find down there.
你不想去可以不去
You needn't go if you don't want to.
-放弃也没什么丢脸的  -不  巴林
- There's no dishonor in turning back. - No, Balin.
既然我承诺了
I promised I would do this.
至少要努力一把
And I think I must try.
你总是不断给我惊喜
You never ceases to amaze me.
-什么意思  -霍比特人的勇气
- What's that? - The courage of Hobbits.
去吧  衷心祝你好运
Go now, with as much luck as you can muster.
嗯  比尔博
Oh...Bilbo?
底下要是
If there's in fact a, um...
真有火龙
a live dragon down here?
别吵醒它
Don't wake it.
藏身于此的恶灵
Cé ná ulco sís nurtaina...
速速现身  现出原形
I ettuluvas caninye! Cánin i sá tanuvaxe!
你来晚了  巫师
来不及了
你的主人在哪
Where is your master?
他在哪
Where is he?
他无所不在
我们是兽人军团
已经结束了
追上他
巫师  光明是不可能
对抗黑暗的
索隆
Sauron!
有人吗
Hello?
记住  这不是家里
You're not at home. Not at home.
要是  好吧好吧好吧
What if...good, good, good.
是这个吗
What's that?
阿肯宝钻  阿肯宝钻
Arkenstone, Arkenstone.
又大又白的钻石
A large white jewel.
真是谢谢你了
Very helpful.
小偷
Well, thief.
我闻得到你
I smell you.
也听得到你
I hear your breath.
还感觉得到你
I feel your air.
你在哪
Where are you?
别害羞
Come now, don't be shy.
现身吧
Stand into the light.
有些不对劲
There is something about you.
你带着什么
Something you carry.
是金子做的
Something made of gold.
却比金子珍贵
But far more precious.
在这呀  躲躲藏藏的小偷
There you are, a thief in the shadows.
我没想偷东西
I did not come to steal from you.
无比富有的斯矛革
O Smaug, the unassessably wealthy.
我只想亲眼目睹
I merely want to get eyes upon your magnificence.
传说中伟岸的巨龙
To see if you really were as great as the old tales say.
我原来不相信
I did not believe them!
现在信了吗
And do you now?
信了
Truly.
传说和歌谣里的描述
The tales and songs...
在你一比真是相形见绌  庞然大物斯矛革
fall utterly short, of your enormity, O Smaug the stupendous!
你觉得奉承我能活命吗
Do you think flattery will keep you alive?
不
No, no...
不能
No indeed.
你好像认识我
You seem familiar with my name.
我却不记得你的气味
But I don't remember smelling your kind before.
你是谁  哪里来的
Who are you? And where do you come from...
请问
may I ask?
我
I...
我来自山下
I came from under the hill.
山下
Under hill?
我翻山越岭  跋山涉水
And under hills and over hills, my path is lead.
来去无踪的我  穿梭到了这里
And, and through the air. I am here that He walks unseen.
厉害  你还有什么名号
Impressive, what else do you claim to be?
我是
I am...
好运随身的人
luck-wearer...
-猜谜能手  -好名号  继续
- Riddle-maker. - Lovely titles, go on.
-酒桶骑士  -酒桶
- Barrel-rider. - Barrels.
有点意思了
Now that is interesting.
你的矮人朋友呢
And what about your little Dwarf friends?
都躲在哪里
Where are they hiding?
矮人  没
D...dwarves? No...
哪有什么矮人  你弄错了
No, no Dwarves here. You got that all wrong.
我不信
I don't think so.
酒桶骑士  他们叫你来送死
Barrel-rider, they sent you in here to do their dirty work,
自己在外面做缩头乌龟
while they skulk about outside.
你真的错了
Truly. You are mistaken...
伟大的斯矛革  猛兽之王
O Smaug, chiefest and greatest of all calamities.
别看你偷东西还撒谎  倒是很有礼貌呢
You have nice manners for a thief and a liar.
我熟悉矮人的气味和味道
I know the smell and taste of Dwarf.
无比熟悉
No one better.
是为了金子
It is the gold.
他们对黄金趋之若鹜
They are drawn to treasure like flies to dead flesh.
你以为我不知道吗
Did you think I did not know this day would come?
我早料到这群虚伪小人
That a pack of canting dogs
会偷偷潜回孤山
will come crawling back to the Mountain.
-地震吗  -孩子  这动静
- Was that an earthquake? - That, my lad...
是龙
was a dragon.
-爸  -山那边来的
- Da? - It's come from the mountain.
别管我们了  带着孩子逃吧
You should leave us. Take your children, get out of here.
逃去哪里  无处可逃了
And go where? There is nowhere to go.
-我们会死吗  爸  -不会  亲爱的
- Are we going to die, da? - No, darling.
火龙会杀掉我们
The dragon is going to kill us.
我会先杀掉它
Not if I kill it first.
山下之王已死  他的王位在我脚下
The King Under the Mountain is dead. I took his throne.
他的子民是我的点心
I ate his people like a wolf among sheep.
我肆意杀戮  随心所欲
I kill where I wish, when I wish.
我的鳞甲坚如钢铁
My armor is iron!
坚不可摧
No blade can pierce me!
-安全  -黑箭  你怎么不早说
- All right. - A black arrow. Why did you never tell me?
因为没必要告诉你
Because you did not need to know.
好好听我说  你去引开警卫
Listen to me carefully. I need you to distract the guards.
我得上塔  将箭上弦
Once I'm at the top of the tower, I will set the arrow to the bow.
-他在这  -卫兵  抓住他
- There he is. - Guards, after him!
快  那边
Quickly, down there! Go!
抓住他
Stop him!
贝恩  贝恩
Bain, Bain.
藏好  不能让别人发现
Keep it safe, don't let anyone find it.
-我来对付他们  去吧  -我不走
- I'll deal with them. Now go! - I'm not leaving.
-拉加  -你被捕了
- Ragar. - You're under arrest.
-什么罪名  -那要听城主的
- On what charge? - Any charge the Master chooses.
-比尔博怎么办  -再给他点时间
- What about Bilbo? - Give him more time.
给他时间干嘛  送死吗
Time to do what? To be killed?
-你怕了  -我是怕了
- You're afraid. - Yes, I'm afraid.
我替你担心
I fear for you,
怕那宝藏迷人心智的魔力
the sickness the lies upon that treasure,
那害你祖父癫狂的恶疾
a sickness which drove your grandfather mad.
我不是我祖父
I'm not my grandfather.
你也不是你自己了
You're not yourself.
我认识的索林从不畏缩
The Thorin I know would not hesitate to go in there.
不能因为一个盗贼耽误了远征
I will not risk this quest for the life of one burglar.
他有名字  叫比尔博
Bilbo, his name is Bilbo.
是橡木盾  妄图篡权的卑鄙小人
It's Oakenshield, that filthy Dwarvish usurper!
他派你来偷阿肯宝钻  对吧
He sent you here for the Arkenstone, didn't he?
不是
No, no, no...
你在说什么啊
I don't know what you're talking about.
不用否认
Don't bother denying it,
我早看出他的祸心了
I guessed his foul purpose some time ago.
但无所谓
But it matters not.
橡木盾的远征注定要失败
Oakenshield's quest will fail.
黑暗到来了
A darkness is coming.
蔓延到了中土的每个角落
It was spread to every corner of the land.
你被利用了  躲躲藏藏的小偷
You are being used, thief in the shadows.
你只是他们手里的工具
You are only ever a means to an end.
橡木盾那个胆小鬼
The coward Oakenshield has weighed
根本没把你的小命当回事
the value of your life, and found it worth nothing.
不是的
No.
你骗人
No, you're lying.
他怎么许诺的  要分你些财宝吗
What did he promise you, a share of the treasure?
好像财宝是他的一样
As if it was his to give.
你一枚金币都不许带走
I will not part with a single coin!
不许带走
Not one piece of it.
我的利齿是宝剑  尖爪是长矛
My teeth are swords, my claws are spears.
双翼一挥  暴风来袭
My wings, are a hurricane.
传说是真的
So it is true.
-黑箭射中了你  -你说什么
- The black arrow found its mark. - What did you say?
没什么  您果然名不虚传
Nothing. I was just saying your reputation proceeds you,
暴君斯矛革
O Smaug the Tyrannical.
您真的是无可比拟
Truly, you have no equal on this earth.
我差点动心  让你拿走宝钻
I'm almost tempted to let you take it.
好让橡木盾受折磨
If only to see Oakenshield suffer.
看他走向毁灭
Watch it destroy him.
看他荒废自己  日渐癫狂
Watch it corrupt his arms, and drive him mad.
不过算了  就陪你玩到这吧
But I think not, I think our little game ends here.
说吧  小偷
So tell me, thief.
你想怎么死
How do you choose to die?
爸  是你吗
Da? Is that you, Da?
橡木盾跑了
撤退
桥上会合
都死了
You killed them all.
外面还有  塔睿尔
There are others, Tauriel.
走
Come.
他要死了
We're losing him.
塔睿尔
Tauriel.
艾瑟拉斯[王叶草]
Athelas.
艾瑟拉斯
你要干嘛
What are you doing?
救他
I'm going to save him.
-你没死  -活不久了
- You're alive. - Not for much longer.
-阿肯宝钻呢  -火龙要来了
- Did you find the Arkenstone? - The dragon's coming.
阿肯宝钻
The Arkenstone.
找到了吗
Did you find it?
快走吧
We should get out.
索林
Thorin.
化为灰烬吧
You will burn!
-跑  -快跑  比尔博
- Come on! - Come on, Bilbo!
走
Come on.
按住他
Hold him down.
愿星月之光眷顾你  赐你生机
Menno o nin na hon i eliad annen annin hon leitho o-ngurth.
蒂尔达
Tilda!
愿星月之光眷顾你  赐你生机
Menno o nin na hon i eliad annen annin hon leitho o-ngurth.
我们甩掉它了
We have given him the slip.
他会追上的
No, he'll still come in for that.
-现在去哪  -西边的卫队室
- So where to now? - Western guard room.
-或许能出去  -太高了
- There may be a way out. - It's too high.
-没可能的  -只有这条路了
- No chance that way. - It's our only chance.
我们得赌一把
We have to try it.
我只听过精灵疗伤的传说
I've heard tales of wonders of Elvish medicine.
亲眼见到真是荣幸
That was a privilege to witness.
塔睿尔
Tauriel.
躺好
Lie still.
你不是她
You cannot be her.
她在远方
She's far away.
在遥不可及的远方
She is far, far away from me.
她走在天上的星光里
She walks in starlight in another world.
可惜只是个梦
It was just a dream.
你觉得她会爱上我吗
Do you think she could have loved me?
跟紧
Stay close.
-完了  -没路了
- That's it, then. - There's no way out.
最后的族人
The last of our kin.
绝处逢生的希望  成了泡影
They must have come here, hoping beyond hope.
回矿山看看吧
We can try to reach the mines.
在生命最后的时刻
My last few days.
不
No.
我不要这样死去
I will not die like this.
畏缩不前  苟延残喘
Cowering, clawing for breath.
-我们去熔炉  -会被发现的  死路一条
- We make for the forges. - He'll see us, sure as death.
分头行动就不会
Not if we split up.
索林  我们到不了的
Thorin, we'll never make it.
总有人能到  引他去熔炉
Some of us might, lead him to the forges.
我们要屠龙
We kill the dragon.
就算是死路一条  也是同生共死
If this is to end in fire, then we will all burn together.
这边
This way.
逃命  逃命去吧
Flee, flee, run for your lives.
虽然无处可逃了
There is nowhere to hide.
看后面
Behind you!
这边
Come on!
跑
Run!
在这边
Hey you! Here!
给多尔戈多送信
橡木盾到了孤山
快去
你  跟我来
这条路
This way, it's this way!
-这边  -索林
- Come on! - Thorin!
跟巴林走
Follow Balin.
-索林  -快
- Thorin! - Come on!
索林
Thorin!
抓紧
Hold on!
快
Come on!
快跑
Go, go!
行不通  熔炉早就冷却了
Our plan's not gonna work. These furnaces are stone-cold.
确实
He's right.
没有大火  没法点燃熔炉
With no fire hot enough to set them ablaze.
没有吗
Have we not?
没想到赢你这么容易
I did not look to see you so easily outwitted!
你变慢了
You're growing slow,
变胖了  老不死的
and fat, you dotage,
糊涂虫
slug!
躲起来
Take cover!
邦伯  拉动风箱
Bombur, get those bellows working!
快
Go!
比尔博  去操纵杆那  等我信号
Bilbo! Up there! On my mark, pull that lever.
巴林  能弄些炸弹吗
Balin, can you still make us a blast flame?
行  一小会就弄好
Aye, it'll only take a jiffy. Come on.
一小会也等不及啊
We don't have a jiffy.
-硫磺呢  -你真的会做吗
- Where's the sulphur? - You sure you know what are you doing?
速度
Come on!
动手
Now!
引它去历代君王的画像那
Lead him to the gallery of the kings.
别停下  比尔博
Keep going, Bilbo!
你以为你骗得了我吗
You, think you can deceive me?
酒桶骑士
Barrel-rider.
你是从长湖城来的
You have come from Lake-town.
这群肮脏的矮人  和运河上的生意人
It is some sort of schemes hatched between these filthy Dwarves
悲哀的长湖城人一起密谋
and those miserable tub-trading lakeman.
只知道射黑箭的胆小鬼们
The sniveling cowards, with their long bows and black arrows.
-我是不是该会会他们  -糟糕
- Perhaps it is time I pay them a visit. - No.
这和他们无关  别去长湖城
This isn't their fault. Wait, you cannot go to Lake-town!
你在乎他们  对吧
You care about them, do you?
很好
Good.
那就看着他们化为灰烬吧
And you can watch them die.
我在这  笨虫子
Here! You witless worm!
-你  -新帐旧账一起算
- You. - I am taking back what you stole.
你斗不过我的  矮人
You will take nothing from me, Dwarf.
旧日的矮人勇士都倒在我脚下
I laid low your warriors of old,
吓得魂不附体
eye in still terror in the hearts of men.
我才是山下之王
I am King Under the Mountain.
这王国不属于你  这是矮人之国
This is not your kingdom, these are Dwarf lands.
矮人的黄金
This is Dwarf gold.
看矮人怎么复仇吧
And we will have our revenge.
我会复仇的
I will revenge, revenge!
我要去复仇
I will show you revenge!
听我说  你不知道什么来了吗
Listen to me, you don't know what is coming?
我就是烈焰
I am fire.
我就是
I am...
死亡
Death.
我们都干了什么
What have we done?